本字幕中文翻译参考自YYeTs YTET
2004年12月26日
On December 26th, 2004, the deadliest
史上伤亡最惨重的海啸袭击亚洲东南海岸
tsunami on record hit the South East Coast of Asia.
世界各地无数家庭的命运从此改变
The lives of countless families all over the world changed forever.
这是其中一个家庭的真实故事
This is the true story of one of those families.
惊天巨啸
老天
Oh, God!
你...
Did you....
我们走之前你有设警报吗
...Did you set the alarm before we left?
有啊 那是我做的最后一件事
Yes, the last thing I did!
不对 我才是最后一个走的
No, I was the last one to leave.
我是最后走得而且我确定自己没有设警报
I was the last one to leave and I'm sure I didn't set it.
不 亲爱的 我才是最后一个出门的
No darling, I was the last one out...
我都设好了 我发誓
and I did, I promise.
- 你确定吗  - 是的
- Are you sure? - Yep!
好吧
Okay!
不 不 我才是最后一个 因为我后来又回去了
No, no, I was the last one 'cause I went back in.
这就意味着警报跟们没设好
And that means the alarm is not set.
因为我没去弄
Cause I didn't set it.
我猜等我们回家发现
Well, I guess that means that we be coming home
一大堆嬉皮士 睡在我们床上
to a large bunch of hippies sleeping in our bed.
那不是跟大学时代的你一样嘛
Well, just like your old college days.
没事 没事 气流罢了 玛丽亚
It's alright, it's fine. It's just turbulence, Maria.
请关闭电子设备
女士们 先生们 我们
Ladies and gentlemen, we are
马上就要在机场降落
about to begin our descent to Phuket Airport.
当地时间为下午1点30分
The local time is 1:30 in the afternoon...
你在干嘛 现在该乖乖的坐好
What are you doing? It's time to sit down,
我们马上要降落了 亲爱的
we are about to land, darling.
卢卡斯不理我
Lucas won't talk to me.
请系好您的安全带
Please fasten your seatbelts...
并将作为恢复到垂直状态
...and return your seat to the upright position.
坐我这儿
Take my seat.
我做错什么了 我什么都没做啊
What did I do? I didn't do anything.
没事的 坐好 别担心
You're all right, just sit down and stop worrying.
系好
Buckle up!
女士 请坐下
Sit down please, madam!
卢卡斯
Lucas.
- 卢卡斯 - 干嘛
- Lucas. - What?!
你就不能对你弟弟
You know you could try being
好一点吗 他只是害怕了
a bit nicer to your brother, he's just scared.
他不老这样嘛 怕着怕那的
So what else is new, everything scares him?
我说他这是遗传谁的呢
I wonder who he takes off, though.
泰国考拉 圣诞夜
Khaolak, thailand christmas eve
拿好东西 别把包落下了
Take your stuff, don't forget any bags.
你们以前来过考拉吗
Have you been to Kalka before?
没有 我们第一次来
No, it's our first time.
这季节最适合再这儿度假了
This is the best holiday season ever.
从早到晚 这里 都很安静
The Holidays starts to full, but this area, it's really quiet.
适合家庭居住
Great for families.
这群岛一周前才开放的 还很新
The archaistic arch is brand new, which just opened a week ago.
- 你们会爱上这里的  - 好吧
- You'll love it here. - All right.
抱歉打断下 我们之前
I'm sorry, but we made a
定的是三楼的 海景房
booking on the third floor, the sea view room.
我知道 很抱歉 我们的疏忽
I know. We are sorry, that was a mistake.
不过这里你们一定会更喜欢
But we feel you might like this better.
- 你们从哪里来的  - 日本
- Where do you come from? - Japan.
你看起来不像日本人
You don't look Japanese.
我在那边的一家大企业上班
No, well, I work for a big company there,
经常搬来搬去
and we moved around a lot, you know.
你呢 你不工作吗
And you, you don't work?
我是医生
I'm a doctor.
现在不行医 就照顾孩子
Not practicing right now. Just taking care of the kids.
明白 你升职了
I see, you got promoted.
真漂亮
Well, that's nice, isn't it?
- 妈妈  - 哎
- Mom! - Yes.
我能喝这个吗
Can I have one of these, please?
卢卡斯 你要是渴了 就
Lucas, if you are thirsty, would you just...
- 喝果汁或者汽水  - 没错
- Use your bottled water. - Exactly.
- 孩子们 过来看看  - 来啊
- Boys, come and see this. - Come on.
看
Look.
- 我举你起来  - 噢
- I will hand it, - Oh!
是不是很美
Isn't it great?
爸爸 我们可以去游泳吗
Dad, can we go swimming there?
可以啊 我们去游泳
Yeah, we could go swimming, yeah.
十 九
Ten, nine...
八 七 六
...eight, seven, six...
五 四 三
...five, four, three...
二 一
...two, one!
我的飞上天去了
Now my name is coming up.
- 是吗  - 是吗 是飞上去了
- Is it? - Is it? It is going up.
和其他的飞的方向不同
It's going a different way than the others.
- 追上了  - 是啊 追上了
- It's catching up. - Yeah, it's catching up.
快看那 直接追上了
Look at that! It's going up directly.
早上好
Good morning.
啊 别弄我
Ahh! Here up!
- 起床  - 你在干嘛
- Wake up! - What are you doing?
快来救我
Please help!
- 圣诞节早晨 - 救命 快来救救我
- It's Christmas morning. - Help! Need some help, please!
我去放礼物的地方了
I go to my gift place in this way.
- 我要出去  - 不不不
- Oh, I need to go outside! - No, no, no.
- 我来啦  - 慢着 一个个来
- Here I go! - Wait, wait, wait! One at a time!
望远镜
Oh, a telescope.
这是一整套新星
A set complete and over
你能把整个银河系 都贴在天花板上
stars in that you can stick on the ceiling.
- 整个银河都搬走  - 我把它安置到最上面
- The whole moves away. - I arrange it on top.
- 快看  - 是条围巾
- Oh, look! - Oh, pool scarf!
我喜欢
I love it!
谢谢你 亲爱的 我是说圣诞老人
Thank you darling. I mean Santa Claus.
你呢 老兄 一个皮球
What about you man? A ball!
棒极了
Oh, yeah!
球进了
Goal!
我睡不着
I can't get sleep.
- 妈妈 我不是害怕  - 我知道
- Tomorrow I get lost! - Yeah. Sure.
我们能出去看星星吗
Can we go outside and watch the stars?
明天吧
We'll get tomorrow.
闭上眼睛 想些开心的事
Just close your eyes and think of something nice.
妈妈 来跟我玩皮球啊
Mom, would you go play ball with me?
待会儿 亲爱的 找卢卡斯玩
In a minute, darling, play with Lucas.
- 真不敢相信 你没救了  - 怎么了
- I can't believe you, the post list! - What?
我会把那玩意儿藏起来 然后不去管它
I hide that thing and I forget where I put it.
我就是在查看一下
I am on it just to check in to
看看有没有从日本发来的短信
see if there is a message filled later on in Japan.
骗子
Liar.
我收到条短信说老尼尔
There should be about text saying that O'Neil should...
的合同要延期两年
have been given us two years of extension on this contract.
这就意味着我们俩的职能重复了
Which means the two of us are doing the same job.
- 那就只有一种可能了  - 他们不能解雇你
- That can only really mean one thing. - They can't fire you.
那代价太昂贵了 别担心
That would be too expensive. Don't worry!
我还真担心
Well, I do worry.
我们承担不了失业的后果 不是吗
Because we can't afford to lose this job, can we?
我可以重新开始工作
I can go back to work.
- 也许是时候了  - 在日本吗
- Maybe it's time. - In Japan?
不是
No.
你想回家
Oh, you want to go home?
这主意也不算糟糕啦 对吧
It's not the worst idea, is it?
我们还需要考虑下
Well, you should think about it.
不过现在我得和孩子们玩儿了
But I'm going to play with the boys now, so...
接着 爸爸
Here, Dad!
接着
Catch it!
抓住它 卢卡斯 继续
Go get it, Lucas! Come on!
亨利 孩子们
Henry the boy!
- 卢卡斯 - 爸爸
- Lucas! - Dad!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
天哪
God!
上帝啊
妈妈
Mom!
救命
Help!
- 卢卡斯  - 妈妈
- Lucas! - Mom!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
- 卢卡斯 - 妈妈 救救我
- Lucas! - Mom, help me!
救我出去
Get me out of danger!
救命
Help!
妈妈 救命
Mom! Help!
妈妈
Mom!
卢卡斯 待在那儿
Lucas, stay there.
- 停下来 - 卢卡斯
- Stop! - Lucas!
妈妈 救命
Mama, help!
妈妈 小心
Mama, take a look.
卢卡斯
Lucas!
看那个地方
Look at that post!
妈妈 你还好吗
Mama, were you all right?
卢卡斯
Lucas!
等等
Wait!
妈妈
Mom!
救命
Help!
我要救你
Somebody to help!
- 抓住我的手 - 不要 不要
- Get my hand! - No! No!
加油 加把劲
Come on! Come on!
- 救命  - 卢卡斯
- Help! - Lucas!
不
No!
加油
Come on!
卢卡斯 卢卡斯
Lucas! Lucas!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
救命 不 不要
Help! No! No!
救命
Help!
- 卢卡斯  - 救命 啊... 啊
- Lucas! - Help! Ah... hh!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
快跑 卢卡斯
Come on, Lucas!
妈妈
Mom!
妈妈 爸爸
Mom! Dad!
救命
Help!
妈妈 妈妈
Mom, Mom.
妈妈 妈妈 妈妈
Mom! Mom! Mom!
妈妈
Mom!
停下来 妈妈 停下来
Stop, Mom! Stop!
求求你
Please.
别再离开我了 妈妈
Never do that to me again, Mom.
- 妈妈 别再离开我了  - 我在这儿
- Mom! Never do that to me again, Mom. - I'm here.
或许你应该呆在那儿
Perhaps you can be over there.
- 抓住那棵树 那边那颗  - 好的
- Come on! Come up that tree, that tree over there. - Yes, yes.
这真是太好了 真是太好了
That is perfect. That is perfect.
小心 卢卡斯 别动
Oh, look, please! Please, don't! Don't move!
就这样呆着
Stay very still.
妈妈 我是个勇敢的孩子 但我害怕
I was a brave kid mom,... but I was scared.
我也很害怕
I'm scared, too.
其他人在哪儿
Where is everybody?
我不知道 我不知道
I don't know, dear! I don't know.
妈妈
Mom.
怎么了
What?
你在流血
You're bleeding, Mom.
天哪
Oh, my God! Oh!
没事的
It's okay.
- 我不忍心看  - 没事的
- I can't see you like this. - It's okay.
对不起 对不起
Sorry, sorry.
你走前面
You go first.
那棵树 那棵大树
The tree there, the big one.
你觉得我们能爬上去吗
You think we can climb it?
好的 咱们走
Okay, let's go.
爸爸
Dad!
慢着 你听到了吗
Wait! Did you hear that?
- 妈妈 我们什么都做不了  - 慢着
- Mom, there's nothing we can do. - Wait!
我们快到了 我们得去安全的地方
We are almost there. We have to get the safety.
不 我们得帮助那个孩子
No, we have to help that poor-
妈妈 要是再来阵大浪 我们会死的
Mom, if another wave catches us down here, we will die.
我们得马上爬上那棵树
We have to climb that tree right now.
走吧
Come on.
- 你在哪  - 妈妈 看看你自己 我们需要帮助
- Where are you? - Mom, look at you, we need help!
我们不能冒这个险
We cannot risk it.
妈妈 我们不能冒这个险 走吧
We can't risk it mom. Come on.
听着
Listen.
如果那个孩子是西蒙或者托马斯呢
What if that boy was Simon or Thomas?
要是求救的是他们呢
What if they needed help?
你一定会希望有人救他们
You want someone to help them,
- 不是吗  - 西蒙和托马斯已经死了
- wouldn't you? - Simon and Thomas are dead!
即使这是我们能做的最后一件事
Even it's the last thing we do.
你在哪儿
Where are you?
爸爸
Dad!
妈妈 看这里 我找到了
Look there, Mama, I see.
你还好吗
Are you okay?
没事了 没事了
Okay, okay.
你叫什么
What's your name?
我是卢卡斯 你叫什么
I'm Lucas, what's your name?
- 丹尼尔  - 好的 丹尼尔
- Daniel. - Okay, Daniel.
你会没事的 我们来救你出去 好吗
You'll be okay, we gona get you out, okay?
把他扶起来
Lift him.
没事的 没事的
It's all right. It's all right.
你还好吗
Are you okay?
没事的 别担心
It's okay, honey! Come on!
别动 我就回来
Just stay here, I'll be back.
- 妈妈 我下来了 等我一会儿  - 不用 我自己能行
- Mom, I'm coming down, give me a second. - No, I can do it.
- 妈妈 我下来了  - 我能行 卢卡斯
- Mom, I'm coming down. - I can do it, Lucas!
求你 就待在上面
Just stay there, please.
妈妈 妈妈
Mom. Mom.
谢谢
Thank you. Thank!
你听见了吗
Did you hear that?
妈妈 看 他们来就我们了
Mama, look. They are coming for us.
在这里
Hey, over here!
喂
Hey!
爬下去 卢卡斯
Climb down, Lucas.
噢 不要
Oh, no!
不 不 不
No, no, no!
等等
Wait!
- 卢卡斯  - 妈妈 我在这儿
- Lucas? - Mom, I'm here.
谢谢
Thanks!
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
孩子们
My boy!
我再也见不到我的孩子们了
I cannot see them, my boys.
我的孩子们
My boys.
不管他们带我去哪儿 你一定要跟着
Do not let them take me anywhere without you.
别担心 妈妈 我发誓不会丢下你一个人的
Don't worry Mom. I will not leave you alone. I promise.
都弄好了
All right!
丹尼尔呢 丹尼尔怎么办
Where is Daniel? What about Daniel?
丹尼尔
Daniel?
卢卡斯 丹尼尔在哪儿
Lucas, where is Daniel?
我不知道
I don't know.
谢谢
Thanks!
Thank you!
- 这里好冷  - 妈妈 这不冷啊
- It's very cold in here. - It's not cold, Mom.
妈妈
Mom.
妈妈 怎么啦
Mom, what's wrong?
我需要抗生素 去橱柜里找找
I need some antibiotics. Look in the cupboard.
我不认识标签 都是泰文
I can't read the labels. They're all in Thai.
应该有英文的 看看旁边
It got to be in English. Oh, look at the side.
仔细看看
Look carefully.
谢天谢地
Oh, thank God!
那边的男孩
See that, boy?
我是他唯一的亲人了 你明白吗
I'm all he's got in the world. Do you understand?
我也是医生 我在流血 你一定要帮我止住
I'm a doctor, too. I'm bleeding. You've got to stop it.
求求你 我需要抗生素 请帮帮我
Please, I need some antibiotics. Please help.
- 你还好吗  我失去了我的丈夫和孩子
- Are you okay? - I lost my husband and two children.
如果我有什么不测
If something happens to me...
事什么颜色的
What color is it?
- 什么  - 我的腿
- What? - My leg.
- 还是红的吗  - 是的 还是红的
- Still red? - Yes, it's still red.
- 那说明什么  - 是好现象
- What does that mean? - It's good.
只要不变黑就行
As long as it doesn't turn black.
你得吃些东西
You need to eat something.
吃吧
Eat it.
- 真霸道  - 不知道是遗传谁的啊
- Don't bossy! - I wonder who I take after.
你好
Hello!
你叫什么
What's your name?
我叫玛丽亚 这是我儿子卢卡斯
My name is Maria, and this is my son, Lucas.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
给她点橘子
Hey, give her some tangerine.
她一定饿死了
She must be starving!
小心
Be careful!
快把头侧过来 不然会呛到的
Turn your head to the side, please. You'll choke if you don't.
来人 来人啊 她需要帮助
Please, please! She needs help.
帮她把头转过去 帮帮她 卢卡斯 快去帮她
Turn her head! Help her, Lucas, help her!
妈妈 你还好吗
Mom, are you okay?
妈妈 妈妈 你还好吗
Mom, Mom are you okay?
你在干嘛
What are you doing?
妈妈 你没事吧
Mom, are you okay?
快停下 妈妈 够了
Mom, stop it, stop it! That's enough!
妈妈 快停下 妈妈
Mom, stop it! Mom!
妈妈 停下
Mom, stop it!
弗朗西斯卡 弗朗西斯卡
Francisca! Francisca!
卢卡斯 看看这里 大家都很忙
Lucas, look at this place. They're so busy in here.
你得去做点什么
You got to go and do something.
帮助别人 你很擅长的
Go and help people. You're good at it.
- 你想让我做什么呢  - 随便什么事
- What do you want me to do? - Just something. Anything.
你能行吗
Will you be alright?
拜托 卢卡斯 我哪儿都不回去
Come on, Lucas! I'm not going anywhere.
- 我发誓  - 好的
- I promise. - Okay.
这是你的家人吗
It's your family?
你在找你的家人吗
You're looking for your family?
你看见他们了吗 本斯特姆
Have you seen them, Benstrom?
冷静点 我来帮你 好吗
Okay, calm down! I will help you. Okay?
我会试着帮你的
I'll try to help you. Okay.
你是本斯特姆
Are you Benstrom?
打扰了 你是莫顿・本斯特姆吗
Excuse, I need to access to Morten Benstrom?
莫顿・本斯特姆
Morten Benstrom?
抱歉 稍等
Excuse me! Excuse me!
我在找我的儿子
I'm looking for my... my son.
- 你儿子  - 皮特・巴里
- Your son? - Peter Barry.
- 没错 他一定想知道我在哪儿 - 好的
- Yes. He'll be wondering where I am. - OK!
皮特・巴里
Peter Barry?
莫顿・本斯特姆
Morten Benstrom?
莫顿・本斯特姆 皮特・巴里 约瑟夫
Morten Benstrom? Peter Barry? Joseph?...
安妮-玛丽
Anne-Marie.
抱歉 能再说一遍你的名字吗
Sorry, what's her name again?
有人叫安妮-玛丽吗
Anne-Marie de Von! Anyone?
拉达・卡斯托里尼
Radha Castorini.
塔蒂安娜 塔蒂安娜・耶诺朱娃
Tatiana... Tatiana Jenochova.
有人叫约瑟夫・本斯特姆吗
Joseph Benstrom, anyone?
莫顿・本斯特姆 拉达・卡斯托里尼
Morten Benstrom? Radha Castorini?
安妮-玛丽・德・布朗
Anne-Marie De Brown?
- 莫顿・本斯特姆  - 是我
- Morten Benstrom? - Yes.
- 瑞典的莫顿・本斯特姆 - 是的
- Morten Benstrom from Sweden? - Yes.
- 我认识你爸爸  - 爸爸
- I know your dad. - Papa?
是的 你爸爸在这儿
Yes, your papa is here.
- 我去把他带过来 好吗  - 好的
- I'll bring him here. Okay? - Yes.
不不不 你得待在这儿
No, no, no, you need to stay here.
我把你爸爸带过来 好吗
I will bring your papa here. Okay?
不 你得呆在这儿 待好了
No! No, you have to stay here, you have to stay here,
这段路很长 你得好好休息 好吗
because it's a very long way, and you you have to rest. Okay?
好吗
Okay?
好的
Okay.
本斯特姆
Benstrom!
我妈妈去哪儿了
Where is my mom?
妈妈
Mom?
Mom!
别 别 你们在干嘛
No, no, what are you doing?
这是我妈妈的床 走开
This is my mom's bed! Get off!
- 走开  - 好了 别这样
- Get off! - OK, come on!
没事的 别慌张 孩子
It's okay! Take it easy, boy!
不 我妈妈在这儿的 她把我妈妈的档案拿走了
No! My mom was here. And he takes her file.
你得跟我来 我会帮你的
Look! You have to come with me. I will help you.
好吗
Okay?
好的
Okay.
你叫什么
What's your name?
- 你叫什么  - 卢卡斯・贝内特
- What's your name? - Lucas Bennett.
你们之前是在哪
Where were you staying?
在...在...
Staying in... uh...
在兰花 考拉的兰花海滩
In, the Orchid beach resort in Khaolak.
还有谁跟你一起来的
Was somebody else traveling with you?
卢卡斯
Lucas?
还有我爸爸和两个弟弟
My dad, and my two little brothers.
你知道她们怎么样了吗
Do you know what happened to them?
有没有其他家人能联系的
Is there somebody we could call?
我外公
My granddad.
他叫什么
What's his name?
布兰恩 但我不记得他的号码了
Bryan, but... But I don't remember his number.
卢卡斯
Lucas?
玛丽亚
Maria?
卢卡斯
Lucas?
玛丽亚
Maria!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
玛丽亚
Maria!
你没事吧
Hey man! You all right?
过会就好
It seems till I hear me.
我马上就上去
I'll be up in a second.
别担心 她们开始用卡车把人往山顶送了
Don't even bother, they are sending trucks to the mountains.
坚持住
Just staying on time, alright?
- 他们很快就来  - 嗯 我知道了
They'll be here soon. - Yes, I know.
- 你能告诉他们我回来了吗  - 好的 等着
- Can you tell them I'm back? - Yeah, sure. Hold on.
小子们 你们的爸爸回来了
Hey boys, your dad is back!
- 爸爸 爸爸  - 爸爸
- Dad! Dad! - Dad!
- 爸爸  - 爸爸
- Dad! - Dad!
刚才有好多好多直升机飞过去了
Out the hallway a helicopter just flew by.
- 是吗  - 是啊
- Did they? - Yeah!
妈妈和卢卡斯
Mom and Lucas...
托马斯 你能下来一会吗
Why don't you come down here a minute, Thomas?
那我怎么办
What about me?
你就待在那儿
You stay and see if you
看看还有没有直升机了 好吗
can see any more helicopters. Is that's okay?
- 没问题  - 好孩子
- Okay. - Good boy!
就快够到了
You're almost stepped right.
踩到了吗
You got it?
我还是没有找到他们
I can't find them.
你是不是看到了很多死人
Did you see a lot of dead people?
我是说真的 卢卡斯
While I'm a very serious ,Thomas.
- 那里面没有妈妈和卢卡斯对吗  - 当然 我没看见他们
- Not mom and Lucas, right? - No, I didn't see them.
我的脚撞到礁石了 好疼
I bumped my feet on the reef, that was really hot.
- 大家都打算离开这儿了
- Everyone was leaving. - Sure.
我们可以走了吗
Can we leave yet?
我希望你
I need you to them...
我希望你帮我个忙 托马斯
I need you to do me a favor, Thomas.
大家都在往山顶上去
It's time everyone going to the mountains,
去避难所 安全的地方
seek to a shelter where it should be safe,
但我不能跟你们一起走
but I can't go with you.
你不能又把我们丢下 爸爸
You can't leave us alone again, Dad.
我得继续去找他们 懂吗
I have to keep looking for them, you see?
- 你得照顾好西蒙  - 我不
- You have to look after Simon. - No!
不行 跟我们待在一起 我没法照顾
No, stay with us, I can't look...
我从来没有照顾过别人
I've never looked after someone before.
- 我好害怕  - 我知道 我知道
- I'm scared. - I know, I know.
我也很害怕
I'm scared too.
但你知道我什么时候觉得最害怕吗
But you know, you know, the most scary bit for me...
- 大水冲过来的时候  - 不是
- When the water hit. - No.
在那之后 我浮出水面 发现我自己一个人
After that, when I came up, I was on my own.
那是最可怕的地方
That was the scariest part.
当我看到你们两个在往树上爬的时候
And then I saw the two of you climbing to the tree in there.
我突然没那么害怕了
I didn't feel so scared anymore,
那时我知道我不是一个人 懂吗
because I knew I wasn't on my own. You see?
如果妈妈和卢卡斯现在孤立无援呢
What if Mommy and Lucas are on their own right now...
想想他们该有多害怕
Imagine how scared they'll be.
- 我们可以一起去找他们  - 不行
- We'll look for those in camps- - No!
托马斯 你得照顾好西蒙
Thomas, you have to look after Simon.
我去继续找他们
And I'm going to keep looking for them.
好吗
Okay?
明白了吗
Do you understand?
喂
Hello.
我能听到
Yeah, I hear you.
我会找到他的
I'll be looking for him.
你们没事吧 有家人走丢了吗
Are you alright? Have you lost someone?
我们没事 只是想尽快离开这儿
We're fine. We just want to get out of here.
打扰一下 我一直在想办法打电话回家
Excuse me. I've been trying to place a call back home.
我能不能用一下你的手机 很快就好
I wonder if I could use your phone? It will be very quick.
看看周围吧 大家都需要帮助
Look around you man, everybody's needing something right now.
电池快用完了 我们还需要用
But our battery is almost dead, and we need the phone.
我明早就去找你们 好吗
I'll see you in the morning. Okay?
- 你不走吗  - 我不跟你们一起走
- You're not you coming? - No, I'm not coming.
托马斯会照顾你的 好吗
Thomas will take care of you, all right?
听着 你们得乖乖听话
Listen to me, you can behave yourselves,
好吗 跟好他们不要走散了
okay? And you need to stay with this group.
我会尽快赶过去找你们
And I'm going to be with you just as soon as I can. Okay?
你们一定要听话
You gonna behave yourselves. Okay?
我爱你们
I love you.
你能帮我照顾一下两个儿子吗
Will you have my boys for me, please?
跟我们一起走吧
Just come with us.
你知道这是白费力气
You know it's useless.
我必须继续去找
I can't stop looking.
我爱你们 明天见 我保证
I love you. I'll see you tomorrow, I promise.
我爱你们
I love you.
玛丽亚
Maria
卢卡斯
Lucas!
玛丽亚
Maria!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
糟糕
Oh, no! No!
你没事吧
Hey man, are you okay?
上车吧 我们把你载到安全的地方
Get in the car. We will drive you somewhere safer.
我老婆本来不打算来泰国过圣诞的
My wife didn't want to come to Thailand for Christmas holidays.
因为我腿受伤了
Because of my leg.
我坚持要来 我的小女儿吉娜
I insisted, my little girl, Ginna.
她才两岁
She's just two.
当时我被巨响吵醒了
The noise woke me up.
发现自己一个人在房间里
I was alone in the room.
我走到阳台看到海水正冲上陆地
I went out to the terrace and saw the sea coming in land.
我花了五秒钟时间赶到楼梯那里
It took me five seconds to reach the stairs,
水就已经漫上来了
but the water was already there.
连五秒钟都不用
It was not more than five seconds.
我在床上发现了我老婆
On the bed, I found a note
写给我的纸条 说她们在沙滩上
from my wife saying they were at the beach.
- 你当时是在兰花酒店吧  - 没错
- You're at the Orchid, right? - Yeah.
水冲过来的时候我们全家都在泳池附近
My whole family was around the swimming-pool when the water hit.
我最先找到了二儿子 托马斯
I found my middle son first, Thomas,
他在一棵很高的树顶上
he was on top of this really tall tree.
我花了好久好久才说服他爬下来
It took me forever to convince him to come down,
他吓坏了
because he was so scared, you know.
后来又找到了小儿子
And I found my little one,
西蒙 他在一棵棕榈树顶上
Simon, he was holding on top of a palm tree.
他只有五岁
He's only five.
我把他们送到山顶去了
I sent them to the mountains.
这样 我才能
You know, so that I can
继续去找老婆和大儿子
keep looking for my wife and my oldest son.
这是我做过的最艰难的决定
Toughest choice I ever made.
- 你打过电话回家吗  - 我找不到电话
- Have you called home yet? - I can't find a phone.
我一直存着电量 就怕万一家里给我打电话
I'm saving my battery, just in case, my family calls.
请用吧
Please.
谢谢 我保证很快就用好
Thank you! I will be very quick, I promise.
- 喂  - 布莱
- Yes? - Bryan?
亨利 谢天谢地 你没事吧
Yes Henry, thank God! How are you doing?
有其他人给你电话吗
Did you hear from anyone yet?
没有 亨利 你是第一个打的
No Henry, you're the first call.
大家都没事吧 亨利
Is everyone all right?... Henry?
玛丽亚和卢卡斯不在这里
Maria and Lucas are not here.
不在那里是什么意思
What do you mean, not there?
海浪把大家都冲散了
The wave came and swept everyone away.
我找到了托马斯和西蒙 但是玛丽亚和卢卡斯没找到
I found Thomas and Simon, but not Maria and Lucas!...
我不知道该怎么办 不知道要去哪找
I don't know what to do or where to look for them!
亨利 冷静点
Henry. You have to calm down!
- 亨利 亨利  - 我得挂了 很多人都需要用这电话
- Henry? Henry? - I have to go. Many people need this phone, okay?
- 我晚点联系你 - 亨利
- I will call you later. - Henry?
对不起 对不起
Sorry, sorry.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 你要我干嘛  - 你不能就这么挂了
- What do you want me to do? - You can't leave it like that.
- 继续啊 打回去吧  - 继续打啊
- Go on, come on. - Go on!
快打啊 快打
Come on man, come on!
再给他打回去
Keep call him back.
- 亨利吗  - 布莱 还是我 听着
- Yes, Henry? - Bryan, it's me again. Look...
我发誓一定会找到他们的 好吗
I promise you I won't stop looking until I find them. OK?
好的
Okay!
我不知道该怎么做 这是场噩梦一样
I don't know what to do, because it's nighttime now, but I'll....
但我会找遍所有的医院
I'll look in all hospitals,
寻遍所有的避难所
and I'll look in all shelters find everything OK.
我会找到他们的 我保证
And I'll... I will find them, I promise you that.
- 找到了我就打电话给你  - 好的
- I'll call you when I do. - Okay.
- 好的  - 好的
- ok! - ok!
多谢
Thanks.
我能跟你一起去吗
Can I go with you?
- 我害怕  - 闭上眼睛 想点好事情
- I'm scared. - Close of your eyes, and think of something nice.
我能坐你旁边吗
May I sit with you?
你多大了
How old are you?
差不多七十四了 你呢
Almost seventy-four. And you?
七岁半
Seven and a half.
你不能扔下我
You can't drop me.
- 他没事吧  - 没事 他就是在睡觉
- Is he alright? - Yeah, he'll be alright.
把谈资盖好 他就乖乖睡了
With a blanket on him, he's alright.
你喜欢看星星吗
You like looking at stars, don't you?
没错 大部分星座我都能找到
I do, stars like most of constellations.
这里的星座有点不同
Here, the sky is different.
有些星球很久很久以前就已经燃烧殆尽了
Some of those stars have been burned out for a long, long time.
你知道吗
Did you know that?
它们死了 是吗
They're dead, aren't they?
它们是死了 不过他们曾经那么闪耀
They're dead, but once they were so bright...
他们的光芒仍然穿梭于宇宙中
That their light is still travelling through space.
我们仍然可以看到他们
And we can still see them.
你怎么知道哪一颗死了哪一颗没有呢
How can you know which one is dead and which is not?
你不能啊 所以这很不可思议
No, you can't. Impossible!
多么美好的悬念啊 是吧
It's a beautiful mystery, isn't it?
卢卡斯・贝内特 能跟我来吗
Lucas Bennett, can you come with me?
坐吧
Sit here.
你叫卢卡斯・贝内特 对吗
Your name is Lucas Bennett, is that right?
- 是的  - 你妈妈是叫玛丽亚・贝内特吗
- Yeah. - And your mother's name is Maria Bennett?
对吗
Is that correct?
我们想让你看看这些东西
We got you to look at those things,
看你认不认识
please, and see if you recognize any of them?
好好看看
Have a good look!
别着急
Take your time.
- 有熟悉吗  - 我不知道
- Does anything look familiar? - I don't know.
你不知道
You don't know?
- 你认出什么东西了吗  - 我觉得没有
- You recognize anything? - I don't think so.
你觉得没有
You don't think so?
卢卡斯
Lucas?
你能跟我来一下吗
Could you please come with us?
妈妈
Mom.
- 你到底去什么地方了  - 你到底去什么地方了
- Where have you been you? - Where the hell have I been?
你去了什么地方才是
Where the hell were you?
你答应过我哪儿也不去的
You promised me you weren't going anywhere.
我还以为你死了 妈妈
I thought you were dead, Mom.
- 对不起  - 我还以为你死了
- Sorry. - I thought you were dead.
真的非常抱歉
We're so sorry.
肯定是做手术的时候有人改错了记录
Someone must have changed her record during surgery.
她怎么样了
How is she?
胸前做了手术处理 不过她失血过多
She had surgery on her chest, but she lost a lot of blood.
现在要做腿部的手术还太虚弱了
She was too weak to have her leg operated on.
等她恢复了还得回去做手术
She has to go back to surgery when she recovers.
但她会好起来的是吗
But she'll be okay, right?
没有 接下来去哪
Nothing. What next?
我们得想办法搭个便车去这家医院
We should try to get a ride to Kathu Apal Hospital.
- 我儿子呢  - 被那些人带走了
- Where are my kids? - They took them away.
- 他们不让我跟着一起走 抱歉  - 去哪里
- They didn't let me go with them. I'm Sorry. - Where?
我不知道
I don't know.
- 我要尿尿  - 先忍着 西蒙
- I need to pee. - You have to wait, Simon.
妈妈 妈妈 醒醒
Mom... Mom. Wake up.
妈妈 你猜我在外面看到谁了
Mom, guess who I just saw outside.
我的腿 我的腿怎么样了
My leg. How is my leg?
还是红的
Still red.
帮帮我妈妈 她的伤口看上去恶化了
Please, my mom. Her wound's looking real bad.
我们正在尽全力
We're doing the best we can.
我们马上就带你妈妈去做手术
We are taking your mom to surgery right away.
五分钟 就给我五分钟 求你了
No, no, five minutes. Give me five minutes, please. Please!
好吧
Ok!
我也不想多占你的时间
I don't want you to slow down.
者是我女儿吉娜和我老婆
These are the names of my little
凯蒂的名字 她是美国人
girl Ginna and Kathie, my wife. She's an American.
- 你能帮我查一下吗  - 没问题
- Would you check the list for me? - Of course.
他们说你女儿有可能在苏拉他尼
Please, they told us her daughter could
这家医院我们已经去过了
be in Surat Thani. We already been to this hospital.
所有的医院我们都找过 就剩这一家了 拜托
We have checked all hospitals. But this one, please.
就五分钟 麻烦等五分钟
Five minutes, please! Just only five minutes!
好吧
Ok!
不会很久的 我马上就回来
I won't be long. I'll be right back.
卢卡斯 卢卡斯
Lucas... Lucas...
罐子里还有东西吗
Is there anything left in the can?
别担心 我去帮你拿点东西
Alright, I'll get you something.
爸爸
Dad?
Dad!
爸爸
- 我要尿尿  - 你憋不住了吗
- I need to pee. - Can you hold it?
憋不住了
No.
西蒙 你去哪
Simon, what are you doing?
快点 他们要把我们丢在这里了 你在搞什么
Hurry up, they're going to leave us here. What are you doing?
- 运气不佳  - 抱歉
- No luck. - Sorry.
抱歉 谢谢你们还等着
Sorry, and thanks for waiting.
那就走了
Okay! We go now.
爸爸
Dad!
是卢卡斯
It's Lucas!
- 卢卡斯 卢卡斯 - 卢卡斯 卢卡斯
- Lucas! Lucas! - Lucas! Lucas!
- 卢卡斯  - 卢卡斯
- Lucas! - Lucas!
- 西蒙 托马斯  - 卢卡斯 卢卡斯
- Simon! Thomas! - Lucas! Lucas!
你们没事吧
Are you okay?
卢卡斯
Lucas!
- 爸爸 - 卢卡斯
- Dad! - Lucas!
爸爸 爸爸
Dad! Dad!
卢卡斯
Lucas!
- 爸爸  - 卢卡斯
- Dad! - Lucas!
爸爸 爸爸
Dad! Dad!
我们走吧 看来不用等了
Let's go, no need to wait.
- 妈妈也在这儿  - 什么
- Mom is here. - What?
他很虚弱 有时会说胡话了
She's very weak. She said some weird stuff sometimes.
护士说会尽快给她做手术
The nurse is going to try operate on her as soon as they can.
妈妈 看看谁来了
Mom, look who's here.
我的宝贝
Hey! Hey, my darling!
妈妈
Mom.
- 大家都没事吗  - 我们都没事
- Is everyone okay? - We are all okay.
- 我快死了  - 不会的 不会的
- I'm gonna die. - No, no.
这个可以拿掉吗
Is it okay to take this off?
- 你回来了  - 是啊
- You came back? - Yes.
现在我可以松一口气了
I can rest now.
玛丽亚 什么 你说什么 亲爱的
Maria, what? What, what darling?
- 我快死了 - 不会的 不会的
- I'm dying. - No. No.
- 你会好奇来的  - 照顾好孩子们
- You're going to be fine. - Take care of my babies.
我不是来跟你道别的
Hey, that's not why I came here for.
你会好起来的
You're gonna be fine as
他们会治好你的
they're going to take good care of you, OK?
我保证我们都会没事的
I promise you we are going to be fine.
- 亨利 我好怕  - 我们会没事的
- Henry. I'm scared. - We're gonna be fine.
亨利
Henry!
我保证没事的
I promise we're going to be okay.
我们要带他去做手术了 现在就得带她走
We're taking her for surgery. We need to take her now.
好的
Okay.
我爱你 你会好起来的
I love you. You're gonna be okay.
我好爱你 我爱你
I love you so much. I love you.
你现在不得不走了
You have to go now.
你知道我爱你
You know I love you.
对不起 我得放手了
I'm sorry, I have to leave your hand...
卢卡斯
Lucas,
谢谢你照顾妈妈
thanks for taking care of mom.
我们俩互相照顾
We took care of each other.
嗯
Yeah.
- 爸爸  - 怎么了
- Dad? - Yeah.
我还有些事没跟妈妈说
There is something I didn't tell Mom,
我必须得告诉她
and I really need her to know.
我也有个家庭
I have a family too.
我一直在节省力气
I've been saving my strength...
因为我还想再次 见到他们
Because I want to see them... one more time.
不 不要
No, no.
一定要用这个吗
Oh, do you have to?
- 我们不希望你感觉到疼痛  - 我怕就这么睡去
- We don't want you to feel any pain. - I'm afraid to be asleep.
医生会处理好的
You're in good hands.
闭上眼睛 想点好事情
Close your eyes and think of something nice.
想点好事情
Think of something nice.
妈妈没事了 卢卡斯
Mom is okay, Lucas.
我们要回家了
We're going home.
贝内特先生 我是...
Mr. Bennett, I'm one of
美国医疗保险公司的
the customer holds for the travel insurance.
我们过来接你们一家
We have sent to take care of your family.
现在没什么好担心的了
There is nothing to worry about now.
几小时后 我们就会到达新加坡中央医院
In a few hours, we will be at Singapore General Hospital.
在那里您的妻子会得到最好的治疗
Where your wife will receive the best treatment in your living.
他们会送你们上飞机 那边见了
These people will take you into a plane. I'll see you over there.
一路平安
Have a safe flight.
我们要去哪
Where are we going?
他们把我们带到新加坡 到那就安全了
They take us to Singapore. We'll be safe there, OK?
请做好在位置上 我们马上要起飞了
Oh, please take your seat! We will be taking off shortly.
好的
Okay.
- 我能不能  - 可以 就一会儿
- Can I just... - Yeah, okay. One minute.
你怎么样
How are you?
就在这儿 跟你在一起
Here, with you.
妈妈 你猜怎样
Mom, guess what?
我又看到丹尼尔了
I saw Daniel again...
他看上去好开心
He was so happy.
被一个人抱着
He was in somebody's arms.
我猜那一定是他爸爸
I bet it was his dad, Mom.
我好为你骄傲
I'm so proud of you.
我好爱你
I love you so much.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
抱歉 您得坐回到座位上了
I feel sorry, but you have to have back your seat now.
系好安全带
Fasten seat belts, please.
- 我不想系  - 不想系
- I don't want to. - No?
在飞机上就得系安全带
You have to fasten your seatbelt in the plane.
我们在海滩上
没事的
It's all right.
惊天巨啸
这部电影根据玛丽亚 基克 卢卡斯
托马斯和西蒙的真人真事改编
惊天巨啸
-=完=-
谢谢观看